Guide to the Thomas Woolner Letters to John Frederick Lewis
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
Thomas Woolner Letters to John Frederick Lewis
1863-1914
1874-1876
MSS.53
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
.42
1 box
The collection comprises 15 letters from Thomas Woolner to John Frederick Lewis, written between 1874 and 1876. It also includes 5 letters from Woolner to Lewis's wife, Marian Harper, one letter from Lewis to dealer William Vokins, and several letters from Woolner's wife and daughter. The letters primarily concern Lewis's declining health—he died several months after the last letter in the collection—Woolner's admiration for Lewis's painting, updates on the politics of the Royal Academy and Woolner's ongoing artistic projects, and current exhibitions. Woolner comments on several works, including: J.M.W. Turner's, Van Goyen, Looking Out for a Subject; Elizabeth Thompson's Calling the Roll after an Engagement, Crimea; Lewis's Lion & Lioness and In the Bey's Garden; and his own monuments to Bishop John Patteson, Sir Cowasjee Jehanghier Readymoney, and Captain James Cook.
Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892
Aitken, Charles, 1869-1936
Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876
Lewis, Marian, approximately 1826-1906
Woolner, Alice, 1845-1912
Woolner, Amy
Biographical / Historical
Thomas Woolner was an English sculptor, poet, and one of the founding members of the Pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood. Born in 1825 in Suffolk, Woolner began his study of sculpture under William Behnes (1795-1864), exhibited his first works as a teenager, and soon formed bonds with Dante Gabriel Rossetti, William Holman Hunt, and others members of the Pre-Raphaelites. In 1852, after some professional difficulty—most significantly, failing to win the competition for a national monument to Wordsworth—Woolner left England to prospect for gold in Australia. He soon returned to sculpting, however, and then to England, where he resumed his work with a portrait medallion of Tennyson and, most importantly, a sculpture of Francis Bacon at Oxford. The latter led to a series of commissions and to increased artistic prominence: Woolner soon bought the home where he would spend the remainder of his life and married Alice Gertrude Waugh, with whom he would have six children. Public statues and memorials continued to form the basis of Woolner's recognition, though he produced some church memorials, as well as several volumes of poetry. He was elected an associate of the Royal Academy in 1871 and would later become a professor, though he never lectured and acquired a reputation for irritability. He died on 7 October 1892.
The main recipient of the letters in the collection is John Frederick Lewis, an English painter known for his orientalist depictions of Middle Eastern harems and street scenes. Born in 1804 and trained by his father, an engraver, Lewis established himself as watercolorist, first depicting animals and later picturesque scenes across Europe. He garnered particular attention for his images of Spain, though this changed in 1841 with the beginning of his time in Egypt. There, Lewis modeled his life after his impressions of oriental luxury, and produced numerous portraits, sketches, and other materials that would form the basis of his most prominent work. He married Marian Harper in Alexandria in 1847 and returned to England in 1851. His painting The Hhareem was a high point following his arrival in England—it reflected a fascination with visions of the orient that would dominate Lewis's output for the remainder of his life. Critics noted the influence on his work of the Pre-Raphaelites, highlighting his use of vibrant color and minute detail, though Lewis himself remained, for much of his later career, physically disconnected from the broader world of art, living and painting in the relative seclusion of his home at Walton-on-Thames. He died in August 1876, after several years of declining health.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Yale Center for British Art, Paul Mellon Fund
Arrangement
The letters are arranged chronologically.
Scope and Contents
The collection comprises 15 letters from Thomas Woolner to John Frederick Lewis, written between 1874 and 1876. It also includes five letters from Woolner to Lewis's wife, Marian Harper, one letter from Lewis to dealer William Vokins, two letters from Woolner's wife to Lewis, two letters from Amy Woolner—Thomas's daughter—concerning the recovery of the letters, and two letters from Charles Aitken of the National Gallery regarding Lewis's paintings. Woolner's letters to Lewis reveal the former's thoughts on his own work, his personal relationships with Lewis and the Royal Academy, his esteem for Lewis's painting, and his thoughts on contemporary art more broadly.
Throughout the letters, Woolner expresses intense concern for Lewis's health—it was during this period that Lewis's health began to deteriorate, culminating in his death in August of 1876, several months after the last letter in this series. Woolner notes his own personal anxiety, while also lamenting the loss that Lewis's incapacity means for the art community. He emphasizes his own admiration for Lewis's work, wondering "what lovely ladies and romantic slaves amid oriental gloom and splendor you are bringing into our life for our delight this year" (1875 January 17). He also remembers "the delightful afternoon at your house; we feel as if we had for awhile lived the life of the Arabian Nights" (1875 July 18)—a comment that echoes those of Thackeray, who, when he visited Lewis in Cairo, described him as a "languid lotus-eater."
Woolner also relays news of the political machinations of the other members of the Royal Academy. While Woolner disclaims any desire for power or accolades, he dismisses younger generations of artists and speaks critically of his fellow academicians. He occasionally provides updates on his own ongoing projects, notably his memorials to Captain James Cook and Sir Cowasjee Jehanghier Readymoney. He references photographs included with his letters, though no photographs accompany the collection.
Woolner describes his encounters with various exhibitions and, on several occasions, asks Lewis for professional assistance. His commentary on exhibits and sales include brief mentions or discussions of Turner's Van Goyen, Looking Out for a Subject; Elizabeth Thompson's Calling the Roll after an Engagement, Crimea; Paul Delaroche's L'assassinat du duc de Guise au château de Blois en 1588; and Lewis's own Lion & Lioness and In the Bey's Garden. He likewise asks Lewis to assist in proposals to protect Egyptian antiquities and to secure the burial of fellow sculptor J.H. Foley in St. Paul's Cathedral.
Art -- France -- Paris -- Exhibitions; Orientalism; Painters -- Great Britain; Painting -- Great Britain; Painting -- Prices; Photography; Sculptors -- Great Britain; Sculpture -- Great Britain; Egypt -- Antiquities; Hayes (Bromley, London, England); Correspondence; Aitken, Charles, 1869-1936 -- Correspondence; Armstead, Henry Hugh, 1828-1905; Boxall, William, Sir, 1800-1879; Butler, Elizabeth (Elizabeth Southerden Thompson), 1846-1933 ( Roll call); Cook, James, 1728-1779; Dobson, W. C. T. (William Charles Thomas), 1817-1898; Eyre, Vincent, Sir, 1811-1881; Foley, John Henry, 1818-1874; Gainsborough, Thomas, 1727-1788; Gérôme, Jean Léon, 1824-1904; Hall, S. C. (Samuel Carter), 1800-1889; Hewitt, D. -- Correspondence; Horton, Joseph, -1927; Ismail, Khedive of Egypt, 1830-1895; Jehanghier, Cowasjee Readymoney, 1812-1878; Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876 -- Correspondence; Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876 -- Health; Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876 ( Harem); Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876 ( In the Bey's Garden); Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876 ( Lion & lioness); Lewis, Marian, approximately 1826-1906 -- Correspondence; Liddon, H. P. (Henry Parry), 1829-1890; Patteson, John Coleridge, 1827-1871; Pope, G. (Gustave); Quain, Richard, 1816-1898; Quilter, Cuthbert, Sir, 1841-1911; Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1811-1863; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851 ( Van goyen, looking out for a subject); Vokins, William, 1815-1895 -- Correspondence; Woolner, Alice, 1845-1912 -- Correspondence; Woolner, Amy -- Correspondence; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892 -- Correspondence; Birmingham City Museum and Art Gallery; Pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood; Royal Academy of Arts (Great Britain); Salon (Exhibition: Paris, France); Society of Antiquaries of London; St. Paul's Cathedral (London, England); Tate Gallery
- John Frederick Lewis letter to William Vokins, 1863 December 25; Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter, signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  "Xmas Day 1863. My dear Vokins, Poor Thackeray has gone! I suppose you saw this morning an account of his death in the "Times". Poor fellow. What a loss! & so young too. At one time I knew him well. Your note gratified me much this morning & when I opened & saw the Photograph, I thought you had put your real self in - & had got somebody to seal you up! Thanks for it - it is very like [...] God knows yet what I shall get by April - I will do my best, if my health holds out - which (I thank God most sincerely) it does at present. The devouring bird shall not find me backward in chucking him tit bits - but he must not be too sanguine - & wait patiently till feeding time. - I will try our friend P. about the girl in the Garden, but as I do not touch that yet, we will say nought at present about it. Do you mean to occupy both houses? or turn one into workrooms? I think your brother wise in his move - Hendon is pretty, very pretty - & I should think his wife wd like it. Besides it will be nice for you & yours to run down to occasionally - Mrs. Lewis thanks you for the Photo. We both write in kind regards & believe [...] to me ever [...] Yours, J.F. Lewis W.V. Esq." William Makepeace Thackeray died 24 December 1863 at age 52.
  General
  With blind-embossed letterhead: Walton on Thames.
  Correspondence; Photography; Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876 -- Correspondence; Vokins, William, 1815-1895 -- Correspondence; Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1811-1863
- Thomas Woolner letter to John Frederick Lewis, 1874 February 1; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter, signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
  "Feb 1 '74. My dear Mr Lewis, I was sorry to miss the pleasure of seeing you last Thursday, but I was afraid you would not be able to come to town again so soon. The election was I think perfectly satisfactory; the new manner of voting acted well, and really gained the wishes of the body by breaking the coalition of several cliques, which are individually of small account, but formidable when combined. I shall be very pleased to have a chat with you on the subject of your pictures, and anything I could do to help you towards some effective assistance would give me great delight; for I have such an extraordinary admiration for your works that I think every bit of your workmanship should be jealously preserved, and every idea of yours on canvas should be made intelligible, even tho' every bit of it may not be by your own hand. I would willingly turn down to see you some day if I could not meet you in town: but I could most likely meet you any day at the Athenaeum if I had a day or two of notice before. Most truly yours, T. Woolner"
  With blind-embossed letterhead: 29, Welbeck Street. W.
  Correspondence; Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876 -- Correspondence; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892 -- Correspondence
- Thomas Woolner letter to John Frederick Lewis, 1874 April 12; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter, signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
  "Ap: 12 '74. My dear Mr Lewis, Sir Vincent Eyre is anxious to do something towards preserving the antiquities in Egypt, and intends drawing up a petition to the Khedive for that purpose, and to have it presented to him thro' the Foreign Office. But in order to give the petition full effect both with our and the Egyptians authorities, he thinks it best to obtain the sanctions and signatures of the President and Council of the R. Academy, and of the Roy: Soc: of Antiquaries. He was speaking to me on the subject, and I naturally thought that you would be the fittest member to mention it to the Council of the R. Academy; if you are willing to bring it forward, or look over the paper with a view to bringing it forward, will you kindly let me know that I may tell Sir Vincent what you say? He saw the Khedive this last winter on the subject, and he seemed anxious also to preserve the Monuments; and would be glad of any external assistance such as English opinion, to assist him in such a desirable object. Sir Vincent says the travellers increase and are knocking things about terribly, and he thinks no time should be lost. I hope you are feeling stronger with this milder weather, and are at work again. Believe me truly yours, T. Woolner."
  Correspondence; Egypt -- Antiquities; Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876 -- Correspondence; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892 -- Correspondence; Eyre, Vincent, Sir, 1811-1881; Ismail, Khedive of Egypt, 1830-1895; Royal Academy of Arts (Great Britain); Society of Antiquaries of London
- Thomas Woolner letter to John Frederick Lewis, 1874 April 19; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter, signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
  "Ap: 19 '74. My dear Mr Lewis, Many thanks for your kind letter; and I have no doubt the R. Academy will wish to support a petition with so good an object. I saw Dobson last evening and he told me the council were not busy now, so that maybe they will take notice of this matter. I grieve to have such a poor account of you from yourself. After such a long habit of close work to be denied it is indeed a loss. But the loss belongs to us all almost more than to you. It will give me great pleasure to meet you any time at the Club you may name. If at any time you came to town, and it would save you the trouble of returning to Walton the same day, I can give you a snug little bedroom where you would be comfortable, and I would try and get [William] Boxall or some pleasant friend to meet you at dinner. I am a bachelor just now; my wife having gone off to the I. of Wight with a little girl who is not strong. Most truly yours, T. Woolner."
  Correspondence; Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876 -- Correspondence; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892 -- Correspondence; Boxall, William, Sir, 1800-1879; Dobson, W. C. T. (William Charles Thomas), 1817-1898; Royal Academy of Arts (Great Britain)
- Thomas Woolner letter to John Frederick Lewis, 1874 May 17; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter, signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
  "May 17 '74. My dear Mr Lewis, your letter was sent on to me at Paris, and greatly delighted I was to know you were pleased with the appreciation of your wonderful picture. You do not think so highly of your own work as your admirers do, or you could not be surprised at any sum being offered for one of your chief pictures. I am sure Mr Graham's offer was bona fide, as he asked me to find out if the possessor would take the sum mentioned, and as he was willing to give it. £10,000 is a large sum, but not much to a man worth £100,000 a year who wishes to gratify a keen taste. He told me he had refused 6000 guis. for Turner's "Van Goyen in search of a subject", and he gave 7000 for Gainsbro's two ladies sold at Christie's last year; so that you see he is not wedded to cash where taste is concerned. My belief is that very soon your chief works will be priceless; that is, they will all become established in first class collections where no money will be able [to] extract them. - There are some delightful pictures in the Loan Coll. at Paris, both old and modern. What a pity you are not well enough to go! - There are the choice works from private houses which will not be seen again by the public. Ingres best works are there. Delaroche's best - the Murder of the Duke de Guise. -A wonderful portrait of a young man by Raphael. Two fine portraits by Antonio More; superb Dutch landscapes, and in fact to have an idea of the wealth there the Ex. must be seen. The knic-knacs are superb and astonishing. - But I will not tire you with an account of all the delightful things I saw. It was particularly pleasant to me, for my wife had never been on the Continent before and everything was new as well as pleasant to her. - Gerome is very fine in the Salon this year, three pictures all equally good. The mass there, of course, being fearful rubbish. The drawing, of which so much is said, is mostly weak, and inexact, and vulgar. - With kindest wishes for your health- Ever truly yours, T. Woolner. Please [...] to answer this. " See: Thomas Woolner, R.A., sculptor and poet, pages 294-295.
  Correspondence; Art -- France -- Paris -- Exhibitions; Painting -- Prices; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Van goyen, looking out for a subject; Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876 -- Correspondence; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892 -- Correspondence; Gainsborough, Thomas, 1727-1788; Salon (Exhibition: Paris, France); Gérôme, Jean Léon, 1824-1904
- Thomas Woolner letter to John Frederick Lewis, 1874 August 29; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892; 1 folded sheet (2 pages): autograph letter, signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 6)
  "Aug: 29 '74. My dear Mr Lewis, The friends of J.H. Foley are anxious he should be buried in St. Pauls, and Canon Liddon tells me that we must have two or three of the chief names in art to support the application: will you kindly send me your aid writing a letter in support of the plan that I may receive on Monday morning. I have to see the Canon at 2 P.M. on Monday to present the letters and help him select the site. You see there is no time to be lost. The Canon proposes Thursday next for the funeral. Most truly yours, T. Woolner. I am grieved to trouble you, but if you can get the letter written your own signature will be enough."
  Correspondence; Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876 -- Correspondence; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892 -- Correspondence; Foley, John Henry, 1818-1874; Liddon, Henry Parry, 1829-1890; St. Paul's Cathedral (London, England)
- Thomas Woolner letter to John Frederick Lewis, 1874 September 1; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892; 1 folded sheet (2 pages): autograph letter, signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 7)
  "Sep 1 '74. My dear Mr Lewis, Your generous soul will rejoice that poor Foley will have the last honour due to him; for our application has succeeded and he is to be buried in St. Pauls on Friday next at 12 o'clock. He will lie close to Turner, Reynolds, and James Barry, with only one grave between him and this noble company. The sterling artists are fast passing away, and what the next generation will be like I tremble to contemplate. - With kindest wishes for your health - Ever truly yours, T. Woolner." See: Thomas Woolner, R.A., sculptor and poet, pages 297-298.
  Correspondence; Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876 -- Correspondence; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892 -- Correspondence; Foley, John Henry, 1818-1874; St. Paul's Cathedral (London, England)
- Thomas Woolner letter to John Frederick Lewis, 1874 November 22; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter, signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 8)
  "Nov 22 '74. My dear Mr Lewis, A letter from you comes like the sun thro' this dingy abomination called fog. It would have shocked me had I known such an idea as coming here this weather had even entered your head as a possibility. So far as I am concerned, election to R. A-ship is a point of no great consequence, as I care nothing for fancy titles, and do not like my time to be taken up by Council meetings, and A.R.A.-ship suits me very well indeed, as I get most of the fun and only a little of the work; indeed none, except teaching in the Life School, which I like. But whether I am elected or whether I am not, I would rather have had your kind and hearty letter, or your solitary vote, than nearly the whole voting of the Academy without it, or with yours in antagonism. - I am delighted to know that you can still work a little, but it is very sad to think of your not being able to walk about comfortably. - I was going off to Venice tomorrow, but the friend with whom I travel caught a sore throat and now I have to wait till his Dr lets him off. - Except a fortnight in the spring in Paris with my wife I have had no holiday this year and begin to feel stupid from constant work on monstrous statues. - I gave your message to my wife; she was greatly pleased and told me whatever I said in return to "imply admiration" - for you must know that she is as great an enthusiast for your work as I am myself. Hoping for you all good, every truly yours T. Woolner." See: Thomas Woolner, R.A., sculptor and poet, page 300.
  Correspondence; Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876 -- Correspondence; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892 -- Correspondence; Royal Academy of Arts (Great Britain); Woolner, Alice, 1845-1912
- Thomas Woolner letter to John Frederick Lewis, 1875 January 17; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter, signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 9)
  "Jan 17 '75. My dear Mr Lewis, It is all very well to say "do not answer this"; but I have too good a sense of my privileges to obey such an injunction. In the "Apocrypha" I remember reading in the days of my youth - "If thou knowest a wise man let thy feet wear his doorstep"; - but as I cannot do this I may help to wear out his door-knocker. Since my return from Venice my time has been wholly taken up or I should have thanked you before for your most kind and cordial letter as to my election. I have, as I said, always had a shrinking from honours and Committees, but now I am in the charmed circle, however I may have got there, I must say that it is most gratifying to find the hearty and friendly way in which I have been welcomed by the members; indeed they could not have more clearly shown their satisfaction; with, of course, the exception of the sculptors, who looked sourly as usual, tho' to them I am always as amiable as one being can be to another in ordinary life. I must confess that if your resolution holds good of not attending any meetings at the R.A. any more one of the main attractions will be gone; and I shall feel as the Liberals now feel at losing the leadership of their beloved Gladstone. But whatever you do in withdrawing from society if it helps to get more work from you I think you may well be forgiven. - I wonder what lovely ladies and romantic slaves amid oriental gloom and splendour you are bringing into life for our delight this year! My wife brought one very little lady into life while I was away in Verona, making four daughters, as well as two sons. - So you see, I must work hard to keep all these mouths at work. Ever most truly yours, T. Woolner." See: Thomas Woolner, R.A., sculptor and poet, page 302.
- Thomas Woolner letter to John Frederick Lewis, 1875 January 31; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter, signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 10)